Guide to the Papers of Bernard Botein 1929-1975 (bulk 1968-1973) MS 68
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Bernard Botein Papers
1929-1975 (1968-1973)
MS 68
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
10.0 Linear feet (25 boxes)
The Papers consist of originals and copies of primary and secondary materials that document the service and activities of Judge Bernard Botein, a prominent Supreme Court Justice of the State of New York (1941-1968) and active court reformist, primarily in the years after his resignation from the Supreme Court. The collection largely presents materials relating to his participation in various legal, civic, philanthropic and political organizations and on committees and taskforces, significantly on the causes of court reform and reform of criminal justice administration. The collection also includes a significant number of manuscripts and drafts of his orations and legal writings; correspondence, including letters from prominent members of the legal and political communities; as well as photographs and other visual materials relating his legal career. The collection also contains published materials including a number of legal publications and official legislative documents.
Scope and Content Note
The Bernard Botein Papers consists of originals and copies of primary and secondary materials that document the service and activities of Bernard Botein in the years of private practice following his resignation as Supreme Court Justice.
The collection centers around Botein’s efforts in over forty-two legal, civic, philanthropic and political organizations and on committees and taskforces on various reformist causes, significantly in the areas of court reform and reform of criminal justice administration in the State of New York. Materials include correspondence, reports, proposals, preparatory materials for studies and research, newspaper clippings and other printed materials including copies of legal publications and legislative documents. The collection presents information on the investigative, commemorative and administrative activities of these groups. Organizations of attorneys, judges and legal educators are represented, as well as community organizations like the Jewish Association for Services for the Aged (JASA), and a number of committees relating to court administration. Information regarding Botein's participation in the political campaigns of George McGovern, John V. Lindsay and Manhattan District Attorney Frank Hogan can be found here.
The collection also contains over eight-six of Bernard Botein’s orations and legal writings in the form of manuscripts and often annotated draft texts that include addresses, statements, articles, proposals, reports and studies, as well as associated notes and correspondence, and relate to his service with various organizations, committees and taskforces. It includes press releases during Botein’s appointment as Presiding Justice of the Appellate Division, First Department for Manhattan and the Bronx (1958-1968), and copies of published works represented in a number of legal journals and newsletters, such as New York Law Journal and Journal of the American Judicature Society.
Additional materials consists of correspondence, including congratulatory letters from prominent members of the legal and political communities, professional invitations, as well as Botein’s letters of support to individuals; black and white photographic prints that encompass the length of Botein’s career (1929-1971), with several depicting Botein alongside prominent legal and political figures; documents concerning the 1969 documentary, The True and The Just commissioned by the Department Committee on Court Administration; and documents pertaining to memorials in honor of Bernard Botein including manuscripts of memorial addresses by colleagues Honorable David W. Peck and Whitney North-Seymour and several articles addressing Botein’s legal career.
Biographical Note
Bernard Botein (1900-1974) was a principal leader in New York City’s legal establishment. A Supreme Court Judge for the State of New York and a dedicated court reformist, Judge Botein was known for his work that liberalized and improved procedures in court administration.
Born on Manhattan’s Lower East Side, Bernard Botein attended Morris High School, The City College of New York and Brooklyn Law School before beginning his legal career in 1929 as an Assistant District Attorney in Manhattan in the Accident Fraud Bureau and as General Attorney for the State Insurance Fund in 1938. During this time he distinguished himself producing many successful convictions for the Bureau, as well as for several State investigations pertaining to state insurance and printing contracts. Serving the State Supreme Court, Botein was elected and served as Associate Justice (1953-1958), and later Presiding Justice of the Appellate Division, First Department for Manhattan and the Bronx (1958-1968). It was during this time that he developed his reputation as an innovative administrator and passionate advocate of reform. Accomplishments include the 24-Hour Arraignment System, a system that lessened the time defendants would spend in police custody, and the centralization of the court system of the State. A strong advocate for equality under the law and the underprivileged, Botein’s work frequently benefited defendants most affected by inequality experienced in the administration of criminal justice.
In 1968, Botein retired after 27 years on the bench. He became leading partner in the law firm of Botein, Hays, Sklar and Herzberg and President of the Association of the Bar of the City of New York (1970-1972). He continued to serve the cause of court reform and was an active participant in numerous legal, civic, political, and philanthropic organizations and on a variety of committees and task forces. He was active in organizations such as the Vera Institute of Justice, the Legal Aid Society and the New York City Rand Institute, as well as the Jewish Association for Services for the Aged and participated in several groups such as the Temporary Committee on Black-Jewish Relations. In politics, Botein was Co-Chairman of Frank S. Hogan 1973 District Attorney Campaign, active in the campaigns of George McGovern and Mayor John V. Lindsay and was one of the sponsors of a lawyer’s protest in 1970 against the Vietnam war.
An accomplished writer and orator, Botein contributed a significantly to the legal field, addressing many in the legal community and publishing numerous legal papers including several novels such as the Trial Judge (1952) and The Prosecutor (1956). In his writings, Botein covered issues such as judicial administration, court reorganization, court modernization, legal aid and pretrial release practices.
Bernard Botein was married to Marian Berman Botein in 1940 and had two sons. He died in 1974 at the age of 74.
Access Restriction
Open to qualified researchers.
Provenance
Donated by Mrs. Marian Botein, 1975.
Related Materials
The Library of the Association of the Bar of the City of New York holds a number of published and translated volumes of several of Botein’s manuscripts, as well as a number of artifacts.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series.
Series I. Organizational Files
Series II. Speeches, Addresses and Writings
Series III. Correspondence
Series IV. Subject Files
Series V. Photographic and Visual Materials
Series VI. Memorials and Memorial Addresses
Most of the material is arranged chronologically within series, except Series I and Series IV, which are arranged alphabetically.
Abrams, Charles; Beldock, P. J. George; Carey, John; Childs, R; Finkelstein, Jerry; Helpern, Milton, 1902-; Hogan, Frank S.; Lehman, Maxwell; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet); McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-; Meyer, Walter; Putterman, David; Rabin, Benjamin; Shack, Elizabeth T; Stein, Andrew J; Stern, Gerald; Academic addresses; African Americans; Articles.; Association of the Bar of the City of New York; Bar associations; Charities--New York (State)--New York; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Courts -- New York (State) -- New York; Crime -- New York (State) -- New York; Criminal justice, Administration of -- New York (State) -- New York; Drafts (documents); Jewish Association for Services for the Aged (New York, N.Y.); Jews; Judges--New York (State)--New York; Law; Lawyers -- New York (N.Y.); Legal Aid Society (New York, N.Y.); Manuscripts; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government; New York (State). Dept. of Motor Vehicles; New York City-Rand Institute; Pamphlets; Photocopies; Photographic prints; Politics, Practical; Race relations; Reports; Scrapbooks; Speeches; Typescripts; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; Vera Institute of Justice; Vietnam -- History -- 1945-1975
- Series I. Organizational Files, Bulk, 1968-1973; 1961-1974 (Box 13, Box 12, Box 11, Box 10, Box 9, Box 8, Box 7, Box 6, Box 4, Box 5, Box 2, Box 3, Box 14, Box 1, Box 16, Box 15, Box 18, Box 17)
  Scope and Content
  Series I consists of materials accumulated and produced by Bernard Botein during the course of his service and participation in over forty-two legal, civic, philanthropic and political organizations and on committees and taskforces, significantly in the areas of court reform and reform of criminal justice administration. In addition, the series contains several files covering others topics including racial and religious prejudice. Materials present information on the investigative, commemorative and administrative activities of these groups.
  Legal groups represent various bar associations and other organizations of attorneys, judges and legal educators, particularly the Association of the Bar of the City of New York (1969-1973), the Vera Institute for Justice (1964-1972), Legal Aid Society (1969-1972) and the New York City Rand Institute (1969-1973). The collection represents several specific committees and taskforces in which Bernard Botein was active including the City of New York, Office of the Mayor’s Criminal Justice Coordinating Council (1968-1969), the Appellate Division for Manhattan and the Bronx’s Departmental Committee on Court Administration (1969-1971, 1973) and the New York State Department of Motor Vehicles' Taskforce on the Administrative Adjudication of Traffic Violations (1969). In politics, materials from Botein's participation in the political campaigns of George McGovern, John V. Lindsay and Manhattan District Attorney Frank Hogan are represented here, as well as civic organizations like the Jewish Association for Services for the Aged (JASA) (1970-1974).
  The series contains original, photocopied, and secondary materials and includes correspondence, reports, proposals, preparatory materials for studies and research areas, newspaper clippings, published articles and other printed materials.
  Some texts of Judge Botein’s orations and writings including academic addresses, public statements, speeches and articles, as well as copies of legal publications and legislative documents are partially represented here, in addition to Series II. Series IV also contains additional groupings of files pertaining to specific areas of research and study.
  Arrangement
  Materials in Series I were re-filed in alphabetical order by organization, committee or taskforce name, and materials relating to the same organization and year were consolidated into a single folder.
  - African Student Aid Fund, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Arbitration Association, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Arbitration Association, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Bar Association: The Fellows of the American Bar Foundation, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Bar Association: Community Action for Legal Services, Inc. (CALS), 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Bar Association: Task Force on Standards of Judicial Administration, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Bar Association, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Bar Association, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Bar Foundation: Institute of Criminal Justice, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American College of Trial Lawyers, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Friends of Boy's Town Jerusalem, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Jewish Committee: Learned Hand Award, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - American Judicature Society: Bernard Botein Award, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Committee on Professional Responsibility, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Twelfth Night Event, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: President, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Special Committee on Judicial Selection and Tenure, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Committee on Memorials, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Committee on Criminal Courts, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Committee on Professional Responsibility, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Congratulatory Letters, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Centennial Committee, Decentralization of Government of New York City Study, Reports and Proposals, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Centennial Committee, Decentralization of Government of New York City, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Speeches and Statements, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: League of Women Voters of the City of New York, Re: State Unified Court Budget, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: President, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: 1 of 2, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: 2 of 2, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: President, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York: Membership Forms, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Banton Boys, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Brotherhood in Action, Inc. I, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Brotherhood in Action, Inc. II, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - City of New York, Bronx County Civil Court: Study on Landlords and Tenant Parts, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - City of New York, Office of the Major: Criminal Justice Coordinating Council, 1 of 2, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - City of New York, Office of the Major: Criminal Justice Coordinating Council, 2 of 2, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - City of New York, Office of the Major: Criminal Justice Coordinating Council, 1 of 2, 1969 January-May (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - City of New York, Office of the Major: Criminal Justice Coordinating Council, 2 of 2, 1969 January-May (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - City of New York, Office of the Major: Criminal Justice Coordinating Council, 1 of 2, 1969 June-December (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - City of New York, Office of the Major: Criminal Justice Coordinating Council, 2 of 2, 1969 June-December (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Citizens Union: The William Jay Schieffelin Award for Distinguished Public Service, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Citizens Union: Regarding Abolition of City Marshals, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Committee for Modern Courts Fund, Inc., 1973 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Council on Law-Related Studies, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Council on Law-Related Studies, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Council on Law-Related Studies, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Council of New York Law Associates, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Council of New York Law Associates, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Courts-Departmental Committee on Court Administration (Appellate Division of Manhattan and the Bronx): Correspondence and Report, Re: film "The True and The Just", 1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Courts-Departmental Committee on Court Administration (Appellate Division of Manhattan and the Bronx): Correspondence, Re: Honorable William J. vanden Heuvel, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Courts-Departmental Committee on Court Administration (Appellate Division of Manhattan and the Bronx), 1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Courts-Departmental Committee on Court Administration (Appellate Division of Manhattan and the Bronx), 1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Courts-Departmental Committee on Court Administration (Appellate Division of Manhattan and the Bronx), 1973 January-March (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Courts-Departmental Committee on Court Administration (Appellate Division of Manhattan and the Bronx), 1973 May-June (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Courts-Departmental Committee on Court Administration (Appellate Division of Manhattan and the Bronx), 1973 July-August (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Courts-Departmental Committee on Court Administration (Appellate Division of Manhattan and the Bronx), 1973 September-December (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Intoxication Problem, 1969, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Housing Code Removal, 1 of 3, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Housing Code Removal, 2 of 3, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Housing Code Removal, 3 of 3, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Correspondence, responses re: Housing Maintenance Violation Code Removal, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Draft Report, Re: Tax Certiorari, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Housing Code Removal, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Selected Meeting Minutes, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Committee Business, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction, 1972 January-February (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction, 1972 March (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction, 1972 April (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction, 1972 May-June (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Correspondence re:diversion programs, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Housing Code, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Membership, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Report, Achieving Prompt Trials in New York City, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Courts-Subcommittee on the Elimination of Inappropriate and Unnecessary Jurisdiction: Notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Federation of Jewish Philanthropies, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Ford Foundation, 1965-1968 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Grand Jury Association of New York County, Inc., 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Institute of Judicial Administration, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Institute of Judicial Administration, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - The International League for the Rights of Man: Correspondence, re: Human Rights Appeal to United Nations, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Jewish Association for Services for the Aged (JASA): Board of Trustees, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Association for Services for the Aged (JASA): Board of Trustees, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Jewish Association for Services for the Aged (JASA), 1972 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Jewish Association for Services for the Aged (JASA): Correspondence, Legal Services Proposal, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Jewish Association for Services for the Aged (JASA), 1974 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - John Jay Law Club, 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Law Center Foundation, New York University: Board of Trustees, 1965-1968 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Law Center Foundation, New York University: Board of Trustees, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Lawyers for Frank Hogan, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Lawyers for Lindsay, 1969-1971 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Lawyers for McGovern, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Lawyers Square Club, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Legal Aid Society, 1969 January-June (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Legal Aid Society, 1969 July-December (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Legal Aid Society, 1970 March-June (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Legal Aid Society, 1970 July-December (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Legal Aid Society, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Legal Aid Society, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Lemberg Center, Brandeis University, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Long Island University: Judicial Administration Program, Advisory Board, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Los Angeles County Bar Association, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Milton Helpern Library of Legal Medicine, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Morris High School, Bronx, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Municipal Art Society, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - National Council on Crime and Delinquency, 1964-1966, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - New School for Social Research: Center for New York City Affairs, 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - New York City Democratic Committee: Jerry Finkelstein, 1969-1971 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - New York City-Rand Institute: 1 of 2, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - New York City-Rand Institute: 2 of 2, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - New York City-Rand Institute: Chairman Judge Botein, 1969 May-September (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - New York City-Rand Institute: Chairman Judge Botein, 1969 October-December (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - New York City-Rand Institute, 1970 January-March (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - New York City-Rand Institute, 1970 April-June (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - New York City-Rand Institute, 1970 July-December (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - New York City-Rand Institute: Correspondence, Report-Rental Housing in New York City, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - New York City-Rand Institute: Court Records, McKinsey Case, 1970-1971 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - New York City-Rand Institute, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - New York City-Rand Institute: Evaluation Report [draft], Ford Foundation, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - New York City-Rand Institute, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - New York City-Rand Institute, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - New York Civil Liberties Union: New York Committee Against Preventive Detention, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - New York State Bar Association, 1969-1971 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - New York State Bar Association, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - New York State, Court of Claims, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 8)